Nikhil Desai

UX Design, Strategy and Management Senior Architect – UX, Digital Process Automation Englishtown, NJ desai.nikhil@outlook.com 848.260.7143 linkedin.com/in/1point1/

An accomplished UX strategist and problem-solver with more than 20 years of experience in transforming applications and delivering design excellence through information architecture, interaction design, and user research.

Work Experience

VIRTUSA CORPORATION, NEW YORK, NY

Senior Architect – UX, Digital Process Automation, May 2007 – Present

Senior UX Manager, COE Advisory — Contact Center Platforms

Client: Anthem, Norfolk, VA **Duration:** March'19 – Present

Drive strategic UX design initiatives across Pega Application Landscape and established the Pega UX COE in partnership with senior leadership to address the usability concerns and provide design direction needed for the success of enterprise contact center applications.

Key Accomplishments:

- Reduced average handling time by 20% through optimization of process workflow.
- Improved contact center associate satisfaction (ASAT) score from 81 to 94 on a scale of 0-100 by implementing intent driven design approach.
- Helped reduce UX debt by 20% and improved reusability by 25% with introduction of Design System and Pattern Libraries.

Role Overview:

- Spearheaded efforts to optimize UX design and workflow transformation for 4 Critical Contact Center Workflow Applications serving Members, Providers and Brokers.
- Established Pega UX Center of Excellence to deliver excellence, consistency, and reusability, while defining the strategic direction for the UX team.
- Advisory and leadership through the UX CoE to ensure adoption of UX standards for enterprise wide Pega applications worked by over 12 scrum teams, while working closely with the Engineering, Business, and Product teams spread across U.S., Canada, and India.
- Mentored UX designers on strategic thinking, advise on development plans, and provide feedback to UX Designers, System Analysts, Product Owners.
- Reimagined existing products, developed new ones, and identified growth opportunities.
- Led the effort to modernize and re-build global DPA UX standards by launching a
 elaborate design system with documentation and pattern libraries used by the contact
 center application product development team to enable the shift towards a modular
 product development model with improved reusability and consistency.
- Lead a team of 4+ UX Designers, with core focus on ideation, planning and execution of UX transformation of Pega-based workflow applications.

Senior UX Architect – Licensing Management System

Client: Wolters Kluwer, New York, NY **Duration:** December'18 – February'19

Led UX design and strategy to establish the end-to-end workflow process design for Business Licensing Management System. Envisioned the future state design approach to help migrate application from Sharepoint & email-based task management to well refined workflow based processed for improved transparency and accountability in the process.

Key Accomplishments:

• Improved operational efficiency by 40% through Digital process automation and reimagined process workflow.

Design Skills

User Experience Design
Visual Design
Rapid Prototyping
Product & Feature Design
Design Systems
Pattern Libraries
Scalable Design Solutions
User-Centric Design
Design Sprints

Research Skills

Workflow Analysis
Persona Development
A/B Testing
Heuristic Analysis
User Surveys
Cognitive walkthroughs
Customer Journey Maps
Contextual Interviews
Guerilla Testing

Technical Skills

Pen and Paper Whiteboard Figma Adobe XD Sketch InVision Studio Balsamiq Photoshop HTML, CSS Pega

Leadership Skills

Project Management
Estimations & Budgeting
Resource Planning
KPI/Metrics Monitoring
Cross-Team Coordination
Team Building & Mentorship
Client Partnerships
IT Consulting & Strategy
Digital Transformation

Senior Pega UX Architect - Ratings Management System

Client: Standard & Poors, New York, NY **Duration:** May'16 – February'19

Successfully Collaborated with cross functional teams of product management, business, and engineering to align the UX vision with business goals for Pega based Ratings Workflow Management System.

Key Accomplishments:

- Reduced application time-to-complete effort by 33% through lean workflow design, translating to an approximate dollar savings of \$1.8Mn per year
- Improved reusability and design consistency with introduction of reusable design templates and patterns.

UX Design Manager – AIG OneClaim Claims Processing Platform

Client: AIG, Berkley Heights, NJ Duration: April'12 – April'16

Led the creation of the interface design for the OneClaims Claims Processing Suite, with a strategy focused on defining the long-term product goals and design directions to align with the organization's UX vision and goals.

Key Accomplishments:

- Modernized the user experience of the Claims Intake and Processing workflow to the new Pega Platform.
- Transformed 20+ interaction processes across global markets like NAM, EMEA and APAC.
- Helped Application Architects define UI Architectural Solutions

UX Architect – Credit Card Decisioning Process Framework

Client: JPMC

Duration: April'11 – April'12

Defined and helped UI developers implement the front end for the JPMC Cards Decision Process Framework, a tool intended for Credit Decision process for Banking division of JPMC worldwide.

Offshore Project Lead - CPM 6.2 Framework Development

Client: Pega Systems

Duration: March'10 - March'11

Played a key role in building and leading team of UI developers, providing technical solutions expertise to help develop the CPM 6.2 framework by utilizing Pega PRPC, Pega UI, HTML, CSS and related technologies.

Offshore UI Lead - Pega PRPC Designer Studio 6.x Development

Client: Pega Systems

Duration: May'07 - March'10

Lead a team of UI developers, with a strategical focus on developing scalable and cross browser compatible design components for Pega PRPC 6.x Platform.

Previous Work Experience

DELOITTE CONSULTING, Hyderabad, Telangana, India

Design Analyst – US Creative Services, November 2005–May 2007

NAVIONICS TECHNOLOGIES, Hyderabad, Telangana, India

Multimedia Designer, July 2003-November 2005

QUADRANT SYSTEMS, Hyderabad, Telangana, India

Web Designer, May 2002–July 2003

Certifications

Pega Certified System Architect PEGASYSTEMS

Feb 2010

Human Computer Interaction

INTERACTION DESIGN FOUNDATION (IDF) October 2017

Publications

The invisible UX of RPA – an insight

Authored for Virtusa Corporate Publication & Pega World'18 Virtusa Market Handouts. https://bit.ly/3hVEyLb

Uncomplicating Design — Taming the Frankenstein Monster of UX

Authored for LinkedIn Blog to showcase the importance of Design Systems & Pattern Library. https://bit.ly/3hFPfBi

Role of UX in Emerging Decentralized Applications on Blockchain

Authored for LinkedIn Blog on the role of UX in blockchain ecosystem as a perspective.

https://bit.ly/34esod1

Education

M.Sc. in Information Technology (M.Sc-I.T.)

VMRF – UNIVERSITY, Salem, Tamil Nadu, India 2004 – 2006

Post Grad Diploma in Computer Applications (P.G.D.C.A.)

OSMANIA UNIVERSITY, Hyderabad, Telangana, India August 2002 – August 2003

Bachelor Degree in Computer Applications (B.C.A.)

OSMANIA UNIVERSITY, Hyderabad, Telangana, India August 1999 – May 2002